in this video we're going to talk about
angular momentum
and the equations that you need to know
associated with it
so first let's begin our discussion with
linear momentum
linear momentum is mass times velocity
represented by lowercase p
so any object
that has speed or that's moving has
momentum so i think of momentum as mass
and motion
so this block that's moving at a speed
of 20 meters per second has momentum
a train moving at 50 miles per hour has
a lot of momentum it's moving fast and
it has a lot of mass so that's momentum
mass and motion
now angular momentum
is very similar
to linear momentum
just as linear momentum is mass and
motion
angular momentum is mass in rotational
so anything that has the ability to
rotate or spin has angular momentum
and angular momentum
is equal to inertia times omega
so it depends on the inertia of an
object which is proportional to the mass
of the object and how that mass is
distributed throughout the object
and also
it's related to how fast the object is
spinning the angular velocity of the
object
and so angular momentum like linear
momentum is a vector quantity
it has both magnitude and direction
so notice the similarities between these
two equations
inertia is basically the rotational
equivalent of mass in that equation
angular velocity
is the rotational equivalent of linear
velocity
and angular momentum is the rotational
equivalent of linear momentum
now there are some other equations to
know
newton's second law states that the net
force acting on an object is equal to
the mass of the object times its
acceleration
then that torque acting on an object is
equal to the inertia of that object
times the angular acceleration
now angular acceleration
is the change
in angular velocity divided by the
change in time
so notice that
inertia times omega
is momentum
so the change in momentum that is change
in angular momentum is inertia times the
change in angular velocity
so therefore we can replace this part of
the equation with delta l
so we could say that the net torque
is equal to the change in the angular
momentum of an object divided by the
change in time
the same way as the net force of an
object
is the change in its linear momentum
divided by the change in time
so this is another equation that you
want to keep in mind
now
we need to talk about the conservation
of momentum
linear momentum is conserved
if
the external forces acting on the object
is zero
so the net external force acting on an
object if it's zero
then the initial momentum will equal the
final linear momentum particularly in a
collision
or in any situation
however momentum can change if there is
an external force acting on the object
but if there's no external forces acting
on even a system of objects
then the total momentum of that system
will remain the same now the same is
true for angular momentum
angle momentum is conserved meaning that
the initial momentum and the final angle
momentum will be the same
if there are no external torques acting
on a system
so if the net torque is zero then the
initial angular momentum will equal the
final angular momentum
so the initial angle momentum is
i initial times omega initial and that's
equal to the final momentum which is
i final times omega final
so if you increase
the inertia of a system
the angular speed will decrease such
that the angular momentum is constant
and if you decrease the inertia
the angular speed or the angular
velocity will increase
so let's say if you have a
merry-go-round
with an inertia of 500
and let's say the merry-go-round
is spinning with an angle speed of
let's say two radians per second
and now let's say if we place a box
on a merry-go-round
so that will increase the inertia
of the whole system because the mass
increased
and so let's say the inertia changes
from 500
to
600. because the inertia went up the
angular speed of the merry-go-round has
to decrease
and you could find the new speed using
this equation
so the initial inertia is 500 the
initial angular speed is 2.
the final inertia of the system
is 500 plus 100 from the box so it's a
total of 600.
and so the final angular speed is going
to be a thousand
divided by 600 so it's going to be less
than 2 radians per second so it's now
about 1.67
radians per second
but the angle momentum of the system is
conserved
it's 500 times 2 which is a thousand so
that's not going to change
if you drop the box straight down
such that it generates no torque
with the whole system
you